Guide to the Marjorie Content Papers and Photographs
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marjorie Content papers and photographs
1908-1996
YCAL MSS 648
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.42
(6 boxes)
The Marjorie Content Papers and Photographs include correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs that document the personal and professional life of American photographer Marjorie Content.
Content, Marjorie, 1895-1984
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from J. Howard Woolmer Rare Books and Susan Sandberg on the Elizabeth Wakeman Dwight Memorial, 1999 and from Jill Quasha on the Eugene G. O'Neill Memorial Funds, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5 (film negatives): Restricted fragile material. Corresponding photograph prints are in Box 4.
Marjorie Content (1895–1984)
Marjorie Content, American photographer.
Scope and Contents
The Marjorie Content Papers and Photographs include correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs that document the personal and professional life of American photographer Marjorie Content.
Arrangement
Organized into two groupings: I. May 1999 Acquisition. II. January 2001 Acquisition.
Photographers -- United States; Women photographers -- United States; Film negatives; Negatives; Photographs -- 20th Century; Photographic prints; Photographers -- 20th Century -- United States; Content, Marjorie, 1895-1984
- May 1999 Acquisition, 1921-1993; 1; 2; (2 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains correspondence, writings, printed material, and photographs by, to, or relating to Marjorie Content. Includes letters from Alfred Stieglitz, Georgia O'Keeffe and others, notes on her husband Jean Toomer, and theater programs.
  Former call number: Uncat ZA MS 621
  Arrangement
  Organized into two series: Correspondence and Other Papers.
  - Correspondence
    - Anderson, Maxwell, undated (Box 1)
    - Babione, Alexandra and Robert C., 1975-1979 (Box 1)
    - Beetle, Dottie, 1938 November 7 (Box 1)
    - Boyle, Kay, 1967-1993 (Box 1)
    - Callawy Editions, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    - Carr, Michael Carmichael, 1922, undated (Box 1)
    - Carr, Michael Carmichael (photocopies), undated (Box 1)
    - Coomaraswamy, Ananda, 1959 June 8 (Box 1)
    - Eldridge, Michael and Cynthia Kerman, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Esherick, Wharton, 1937-1963 (Box 1)
    - Forrester, Besty and Bobby, 1952, undated (Box 1)
    - Grant, Kenneth Gordon, 1938-1982, undated (Box 1)
    - Gunn, Marian, 1961-1980 (Box 1)
    - Hampton, Druska, 1924, undated (Box 1)
    - India Journal [empty] (Box 1)
    - India trip, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Jenks, Jo Ben-Shmuel, 1964-1974 (Box 1)
    - Loeb, Harold, 1925-1974 (Box 1)
    - Loeb, James, 1960-1964 (Box 1)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1921-1984; 2 (Box 1)
    - Mowbray-Clarke, Helen Bothwell Horgan, 1921-1962 (Box 1)
    - O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1933-1987, undated (Box 1)
    - Patel, M. S., 1967-1971 (Box 1)
    - Poor, Bessie Breuer, 1935-1975 (Box 1)
    - Putnam, Wallace, 1951-1978, undated (Box 1)
    - Ridge, Lola, 1935-1941 (Box 1)
    - Robus, Hugo, 1939-1964 (Box 1)
    - Robus, Hugo [Roberta (Bobbi) K. Tarbell], 1978-1980 (Box 1)
    - Sandberg, Eric and Trish, 1962-1976 (Box 1)
    - Sandberg, Keith and Nan, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Sandberg, Michael, 1959-1980 (Box 1)
    - Sandberg, Susan, 1931-1982; 9 (Box 1)
    - Stieglitz, Alfred, 1920-1924 (Box 1)
    - Toomer, Jean, 1967-1996 (Box 1)
    - "Toomer Papers", 1984-1986 (Box 1)
    - Toomer, Marjorie Content, 1905-1983; 2 (Box 1)
    - United States. Department of the Interior. Office of Indian Affairs, 1933-1935 (Box 1)
    - Weniger, Maria, 1935-1959 (Box 1)
  - Other Papers
    - "American Indians", 1958, undated (Box 2)
    - "Background ", 1983, undated (Box 2)
    - "Barn remodeling 1955", 1955-1979 (Box 2)
    - "Clippings, etc.", 1911-1984 (Box 2)
    - "Clippings, personal", 1960-1974 (Box 2)
    - "The Gold Finch", 1914 (Box 2)
    - "Interview with Rick Howe", 1984 May 24 (Box 2)
    - "Journal of Voyage", undated; 6 (Box 2)
    - "Life with Jean Toomer", undated (Box 2)
    - MCT (Box 2)
      Includes typescript drafts of writings, early journal of Content's, and photographs
    - "Mill House Notes. 'Psychotic Journal'", 1936-1946 (Box 2)
    - "Miscellaneous thoughts and quotes", 1936, undated (Box 2)
    - "Notebook", 1942, undated (Box 2)
    - Notes, undated (Box 2)
    - "Georgia O'Keeffe", 1980-1981, undated (Box 2)
    - Printed material, 1908-1919; 2 (Box 2)
    - Theatrical "career" including material on Theatre Guild, Special Matinees, The Miracle, and Sunwise Turn, 1922-1974 (Box 2)
- January 2001 Acquisition, 1939, undated; 2; 1; (3 boxes)
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 103
  Contains photographs of members of the Toomer family and photographs from Content's travel to India.
  Organized into two series: Toomer Family Photographs and "Year in India" Photographs and Film Negatives.
  - Toomer Family Photographs
    - 42 photographs of Jean Toomer and the Toomer family, undated; 5 (Box 3)
      Many with manuscript annotations on verso.
  - "Year in India" Photographs and Film Negatives
    Conditions Governing Access
    Box 5 (film negatives): Restricted fragile material. Corresponding photograph prints are in Box 4.
    Photographs and negatives are housed in numbered envelopes. Numbers preceding photograph and negative descriptions correspond to the numbers on envelopes. All photographs have corresponding negatives unless otherwise noted. Numbers following descriptions represent the numbered prints and negatives. Photographs have manuscript annotations on verso.
    - 1: Sue and On the Farm #1-24, 1939 (Box 4)
      Seven negatives without prints: #18-24. These negatives were scanned and surrogate copies are filed with the prints.
    - 2: On board the Queen Mary #25-25 (Box 4)
    - 3: London/Canterbury #36-46 (Box 4)
      - #36-37 London
      - #38 Arge on train to Canterbury
      - #39 etc.-Canterbury
    - 4: Jordans #47-61 (Box 4)
    - 5: M. S. Balorean sailed August 4 from Southampton #62-82 (Box 4)
      - #62-67 ship
      - #68-70 Arge
      - #71-82 children
    - 6: Lisbon #83-87 (Box 4)
    - 7: Tangiers #88-109 (Box 4)
    - 8: Marseilles/Gibraltar/Spanish Coast #110-114 (Box 4)
    - 9: Port Said #115-123 (Box 4)
    - 10: Suez Canal # 124-134 (Box 4)
    - 11: Socotra Monsoon #135-138 (Box 4)
    - 12: Colombo arrival Aug. 24th #139-146 (Box 4)
    - 13: Colombo #147-155 (Box 4)
    - 14: Galle Face (Box 4)
      - #156-170
      - #165 Arge
      - #166-7-Sinhalese waiters
      - #168 Kodi
      - #169-70-JT
    - 15a: Buddhist Temples (Box 4)
      - #171-180
      - #171-172 Asokarama
      - #173-180 Kelani
    - 15b: Perahera From a distance #181-197 (Box 4)
    - 16: Perahera Nearer #198-208 (Box 4)
    - 17: Perahera still closer #209-221 (Box 4)
    - 18: Kandy #222-245 (Box 4)
    - 19: Dhanushkopdi S. India Tirurannamalai Madras #246-260 (Box 4)
    - 20: Calcutta Santiniketan #261-270 (Box 4)
    - 21: Darjeeling I #271-287 (Box 4)
    - 22: Darjeeling II #288-300 (Box 4)
      - Market Bldgs
      - Bellevue
      - Pony Women, etc.
    - 23: Ghoom I #301-312 (Box 4)
    - 24: Ghoom II #313-326 (Box 4)
    - 25: Benares #327-348 (Box 4)
      - #331-342 on the Ganges
      - #343-5 Hotel Cecil
      - #346-8 Snake charmer
    - 26: Sarnath Allahabad #356 #349-356 (Box 4)
    - 27: At Laurie's Hotel, Agra I #357-368 (Box 4)
      - Deer
      - Swimming Pool
      - Anne & Arge
    - 28: At Laurie's Hotel, Agra II #369-382 (Box 4)
      - Elizabeth and Ayah
      - Magician
      - Bird Man
    - 29: The Taj Agra #383-395 (Box 4)
    - 30: Agra Fort I #396-416 containing Golden Pavilons, views toward Taj, Mina Mosque (Box 4)
    - 31: Agra Fort II. #417-439 containing Hall of Public Audience, Mirror Palace, Big Court, Peal Mosque, Exit- JT (Box 4)
    - 32: Delhi #440-449 (Box 4)
      - #440 Diwali
      - Some of Hotz collection
      - #448-9 Sikh
    - 33: Delhi Jami Masjid #450-460 (Box 4)
    - 34: Bombay #461-466 (Box 4)
    - 35: Bombay Durant's Farm-#467-476 (Box 4)
    - 36: Leaving Bombay on The Anyo Maru #477-485 (Box 4)
    - 37: On board Anyo Maru #486-496 (Box 4)
    - 38: Colombo #497-506 (Box 4)
      - Mt. Lavinia
      - Munasingha
      - Jacob's room Isabel Court
    - 39: Colombo Last Days and departure #507-521 (Box 4)
    - 40: On board Conte Biancamano #522-532 (Box 4)
    - 41: Singapore and 3 ??? #533-538 (Box 4)
    - 42: Hong Kong and Kaoloon #539-556 (Box 4)
    - 43: Manila #557-566 (Box 4)
    - 44: Shanghai #567-574 (Box 4)
    - 45: Tuata Maru #575-589 (Box 4)
    - 46: Honolulu #570-599 (Box 4)
    - 47: San Francisco (The mainland) #600-611 (Box 4)
      - #600-607 coming in
      - #608-611 at Susan's
    - 48: In Utah #612-623 (Box 4)
    - 49: Mormon Tabernacle and Garfield Smelter #624-629 (Box 4)
    - 50: SouthWest #630-639 (Box 4)
    - 51: Taos/Santa Fe #640-654 (Box 4)
      - #640-643 Taos
    - 52: Washington, Pa.#655 (Box 4)
    - Film negatives (Box 5)
  - Wooden box that originally contained photographs and negatives (Box 6)
  - Restricted Fragile
    Restricted fragile material. Corresponding photographic prints are in Box 4. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
    - Film negatives (Box 5)